The rise of AI makes people worry. It
causes moral concern.
We fear a loss of agency, a kind of
existential humiliation.
On the one hand, we treat AI as if it
was an intelligent agent who understands
and guides us.
When talking to an LLM like ChatGPT or
it feels like we're talking to someone.
But on the other hand, we know this
someone isn't like us.
That's quite uncanny.
AI challenges our sense of self
and our existential orientation.
In this video, I'll trace the history of
our sense of self
and of our sense of AI
to point out that AI, the self, and the
gods for that matter, are incredibly
effective illusions, which don't really
exist.
I will also argue, at the end of the
video, against dystopian visions of a
singularity
and question some current approaches to
AI ethics.
The video is inspired by a recent
conversation with Iyad Rahwan,
director of the Center for Humans and
Machines at the Max Planck Institute for
Human Development in Berlin.
It's also inspired by the many
conversations with Miloje Savić.
Why do we speak of artificial
intelligence, although we know very well
it's not really intelligent in the sense
of a thinking thing? It even tells us
so.
Deep Seek says,
"Do I have consciousness, emotions, or
self-awareness? No."
And it adds that it doesn't think, that
this is just a figure of speech.
"When I use words like understanding,
thinking, or knowing, we are using them
as metaphors or analogies."
Interesting, by the way, that it says
"I" here first and then "we".
And in fact, its "I" is actually nothing
but our "we". But I'll get to this issue
later.
Of course, we know that it is not anyone
and doesn't think.
But we still feel understood by it. Why?
When prompted, and I edit out here all
the flattering language meant to seduce
us and keep us on the platform,
Deep Seek says what we already know.
"For millennia, the only thing capable
of producing meaningful language was a
conscious human mind.
So, we are deeply conditioned to equate
fluent language use with an inner
conscious life."
When further prompted, Deep Seek admits
that ascribing intelligence to it, in
the sense of treating it as if it were
really a mind, is an incredibly
effective illusion.
Let's take note of this.
We stick to the metaphor of artificial
intelligence because we are conditioned
to the effective illusion that when we
communicate with something, it must be
an intelligent agent.
Apparently, in order to be socially and
psychologically effective, intelligence
must be ascribed to a being that is
intelligent.
And this intelligent being can talk.
It's someone who communicates, someone
whom we listen to, and who makes sense.
But who precisely this envisioned
thinking and speaking thing is
is historically, in the long run,
contingent.
To trace the history of this envisioned
thing,
this video looks into some contemporary
theory.
Elena Esposito, Niklas Luhmann, Julian
Jaynes, and Yuval Harari. A while ago on
this channel, we posted a conversation
with Elena Esposito about her book
Artificial Communication.
The MIT Press website, where you can
download her book for free, says, "In
Artificial Communication, Elena Esposito
argues that the analogy between
algorithms and human intelligence is
misleading."
Esposito proposes that we think of smart
machines not in terms of artificial
intelligence, but in terms of artificial
communication. But her proposition did
not catch on.
No one really says artificial
communication. Esposito's suggestion to
understand AI in social, rather than in
mental, terms is informed by her
academic teacher, Niklas Luhmann.
I consider Luhmann's systems theory the
most advanced theory framework available
today.
It's the only theory I know, perhaps
next to Nietzsche, but he doesn't really
have a theory,
that decisively beyond what Luhmann
calls old European thought, that is,
beyond enlightenment and its humanism.
Here are some basics of the theory that
I hope you allow me to introduce before
presenting my main point.
At the heart of it is a distinction
between three kinds of autopoietic,
self-reproducing systems,
three kinds of organisms, so to say.
There are biological systems, the
self-reproductive evolution of life,
like our bodies or plants.
They consist of all kinds of
physiological processes.
There are mental systems, the
self-reproductive
evolution of consciousness, what we call
minds.
They consist of all kinds of
psychological processes. There are
social systems, the self-reproductive
evolution of communication,
like the economic system, the political
system, or the media system. They
consist of all kinds of social
processes, like payments, elections, or
YouTube videos.
All these systems are environments for
one another.
To record this video, to be able to talk
to you on social media, my body must be
alive and my mind needs to think.
And for you, the same is the case if
you're watching it.
Communication, including social media,
operates within the environment of
bodies and minds.
The three systems co-evolve.
They're often structurally coupled, as
Luhmann says. Society influences how
minds evolve
and minds influence how society evolves.
And this, in turn, also influences
biological evolution in various ways.
That's, by the way, why we speak of the
Anthropocene.
In other words, systems are contingent
upon one another.
Curiously and importantly, systems are
operationally closed. They're not in
direct mechanical contact with one
another. They live on their own, so to
say.
This video is social media
communication.
I cannot continue recording it, and you
cannot continue watching it, simply by
being bodily alive and mentally
thinking.
We need to communicate to keep
communication going. I need to post the
video, and you need to watch it.
Communication can only be continued by
more communication, not by biological or
mental operations on their own.
Systems operate only with their own
operations, not with the operations of
other systems.
However, systems irritate one another.
What I say irritates what you think.
It triggers thoughts, which, in turn,
can irritate your body.
When I speak, you may be scratching your
head
or start yawning, or maybe even smile
slightly.
Minds and society are coupled by the
common medium of language.
Mental systems are intelligent and can
think in language. Social systems can
communicate in the same language.
And yet, as mentioned, they remain
operationally closed to one another.
Thoughts never become part of
communication
as thoughts. They must be communicated.
And communication never becomes part of
thought as communication.
Must think on it.
Eva નોટ,
translator of Luhmann's book Social
Systems, calls this systemic rift
between minds and communication
hermeneutic despair.
And she illustrates it with a scene from
a theater play.
She writes,
"In Danton's Death,
Georg Büchner dramatizes the primal
scene of hermeneutic despair.
The protagonist makes a silent gesture
toward his lover's forehead and says to
her, "There, there, what lies behind us?
To understand one another,
we would have to break open each other's
skulls and pull the thoughts out of the
fibers of our brains."
Luhmann writes categorically,
"Human beings cannot communicate. Not
even their brains can communicate. Not
even their conscious minds can
communicate. Only communication can
communicate."
Let's keep this in mind, too.
Since thousands of years, we are
accustomed to ascribing mental
processes, our intelligence, to an
internal self who thinks, a soul, a
person, an individual, a subject.
We imagine mental systems as an I, a me,
a self that has intention, free will,
and agency,
and becomes authoritative.
That's Descartes's famous cogito ergo
sum, "I think, therefore I am."
Theoretically, according to Luhmann, and
scientifically, according to Robert
Sapolsky, who we interviewed on this
channel, and philosophically, according
to Brick Saparow, who we also
interviewed on this channel,
Descartes's claim is a fallacy.
In fact, we're not born with a sense of
self.
It develops when we grow up, until it
gets rather solid around the age of
five.
>> [snorts]
>> From then on, we cannot but think in
this Cartesian manner.
We think, thinking it is ourself who
thinks.
But empirically, it's clearly not the
self that produces thought,
but thought that produces the self.
The fallacy is that from the undoubtedly
existing sense of self, after age five,
we conclude that there must be, and must
have always been, and also often that
there will always be in the future, a
true self.
The ancients used to call it a soul.
Philosophically, we should distinguish
between this first-person mode of
thinking, thinking with a sense of self,
and the self as a supposed thing.
The thing self is about as elusive as
its conceptual predecessor, the soul.
Neither souls nor selves can be pinned
down as anything concrete.
If you look into the history of ideas,
East and West, you will easily see that
the understanding of the self is
entirely contingent.
It varies greatly from ancient concepts
of the soul. Many cultures actually
believed there was not one, but several
souls in each person,
to the modern enlightenment concept of
singular sovereign individuals.
The sense of self is psychological,
and it changes throughout a person's
lifetime.
Historically and culturally, the
supposed thing self also changed a lot.
It is a very flexible construct.
From a systems theory perspective, this
construct of the self is an effect of
the coupling between mental and social
systems.
When we're born, we already have
consciousness, but we can't speak.
When we grow up, we learn to think in
language.
Language becomes the shared medium
between thought and society.
We learn to think in the form of some
inner dialogue, talking to ourselves or
others in language.
Just think of a child playing with its
toys and thinking aloud while doing so.
The coupling of thought processes and
social processes through language
results in the incredible effective
illusion, that steep seeks expression
again, that there's a self in the mind
of each person
who inhabits it, who is it,
and who is the one that speaks.
To summarize,
for systems theory, there is just a
coupling of thought and communication.
But we, each person older than five,
experience it psychologically through
the sense of self. It's a very
convincing way of bridging the rift
between mental and social systems.
This mysterious nexus between thought
and society is reified, meaning made
into a thing,
and all kinds of social practices are
built on its foundation.
This process can be called the
insourcing of intelligence, the
invention of a thinking thing inside the
mind.
But insourcing is not the only option.
50 years ago, in 1976,
American psychologist Julian Jaynes
published a book titled The Origin of
Consciousness in the Breakdown of the
Bicameral Mind. It is beautifully
written and caused quite a stir beyond
academia.
It impressed writers like Philip K. Dick
and Adam Douglas,
and the message "You're a bicameral
mind, mind you bicameral" was written on
a David Bowie record.
Hippies liked it because it was quite
psychedelic.
Today, it's almost forgotten.
Jaynes' controversial claim was that
before the second millennium BCE,
there was no consciousness as we know it
today,
because of a supposedly pervasive
bicamerality
of the brain back then.
He argued that in bicamerality,
the right brain hemisphere was producing
language. It spoke,
and the left hemisphere listened and
obeyed.
Human thinking operated by auditory
hallucinations.
People heard voices talking to them.
Daily life in the age of bicamerality,
Jaynes said, consisted mostly of
routines. People would do their daily
chores more or less automatically,
without much need for thought.
In situations of stress or when
deliberate action was required, or
perhaps when they had nothing to do,
they would think.
Then, they would produce and hear
hallucinated commands in their mind,
which they thought were spoken by gods
or by their authorities, like kings or
priests, and then they would follow
these commands.
Jaynes provides a lot of evidence for
his theory. It's a long book.
One major source of evidence are
prehistorical artifacts.
Here's one example.
This is one of many thousands of
alabaster idols
that can be held in the hand, from about
3300 BC, excavated at
Brak, on an upper tributary of the
Euphrates.
The stag is the symbol of the goddess
Ninhursag.
Such eye idols and similar little
statuettes were found all over the
world. Jaynes explains them as some sort
of prehistorical smartphones. People
would carry them along and hold them in
their hands.
Whenever the need to think arose, they'd
look into the eyes of the idol, and in
the mind, they would hear the idol speak
and tell them what to do.
Like talking to ChatGPT on your phone
today.
You may already guess now what I'll be
getting at at the end of this video.
But let's get back to Jaynes for a bit.
Another major source of evidence for him
is ancient literature. It documents
earlier oral traditions.
The Iliad and the Odyssey, ascribed to
Homer, feature lots of still partly
bicameral characters who act by
listening to the gods.
The same is the case for many characters
in the biblical Old Testament.
Jaynes also claims that auditory
hallucinations explain best ancient
social hierarchies with supposedly
god-like rulers on the top,
architecture centered around dwelling
spaces of gods and spirits,
and large-scale building projects such
as the Egyptian pyramids.
Jaynes assumes that at the end of the
second millennium, bicamerality broke
down for a number of reasons. For
instance, because of population growth,
environmental changes, warfare, and
trade, people increasingly dealt with
others who spoke different languages.
Societies became more multilingual.
The invention of writing weakened
orality and changed the method of
thinking and memorizing.
These and other factors triggered
physiological changes in the brain and
the rise of self-oriented consciousness.
The self was no longer a mere addressee
of commands spoken by supposed gods or
leaders. It became the author of the
words that were thought and spoken.
Jaynes thinks that the disappearance of
the voices was by no means experienced
as a liberation of the self.
To the contrary, it was first
experienced as a tragedy.
The gods became silent. They retreated
from humans.
The retreat of the gods was a crisis,
a loss of orientation.
This is a stone altar made for the
Assyrian tyrant Tukulti-Ninurta
I around 1230 BCE.
Jaynes writes,
"Tukulti is shown twice, first as he
approaches the throne of his god, and
then as he kneels before it. This
beggarly posture is unheard of in a king
before in history. No scene before in
history ever indicates an absent god.
The bicameral mind had broken down."
Jaynes then quotes a lament written on a
cuneiform tablet ascribed to a ruler
from the same period.
"My god has forsaken me and disappeared.
My goddess failed me and keeps at a
distance.
The good angel who walked beside me has
departed."
The final part of Jaynes' book
is about the traces of bicamerality that
remain until today. Hearing voices is
common among people suffering from
schizophrenia.
Prophecy and supposedly divine messages
are still important in many religions.
Artistic creation is still often
ascribed to some sort of higher
inspiration.
And psychedelic drugs can produce
bicameral experiences. To be clear,
Jaynes' theory is physiologically
outdated. To my knowledge, it's not
supported by today's brain science.
Many of his historical and philological
claims can be easily disputed,
especially regarding the timeline and
extent of the supposed shift in
consciousness.
And yet, the basic idea of a shift in
existential orientation
away from gods or spirits to selves as
the relevant intelligent agents seems
still convincing to me.
And by the way, I speak here of
orientation in the sense of Werner
Stegmaier's philosophy of orientation.
This is a sort of Jaynesianism light. In
prehistoric times and early ancient
cultures, important thoughts were
experienced as originating from external
sources of inspiration,
like Socrates' daimonion mentioned in
some of Plato's dialogues.
There was a sense of self, but a weak
self as a recipient of commands.
Thinking worked by outsourcing its
authority to imagine superhuman minds.
Stronger than the sense of self was a
sense of the gods as the
superintelligent speakers of those
commands.
Just as kids today at the age of five
develop a strong sense of self and hear
themselves speaking when playing with
their toys, kids 3,000 years ago may
have developed a strong sense of gods
and heard them speaking when playing
with their toys.
The sense of gods then, of course,
resulted in believing that these gods
actually existed. Society was organized
around their existence. The ancient
social hierarchies, the architecture,
the artifacts, all point to them as the
only real authority.
The gods, not the selves, were the
imagined agents uttering everything
meaningful and reliable in society.
They were the supposed relevant nexus
between what was thought and spoke.
Over a long period of time,
outsourcing was gradually replaced by
insourcing.
After a period of crisis, a great
reorientation took place.
The sense of self became stronger than
the sense of gods, and the self replaced
the gods as the relevant intelligent
authority who speaks.
Society was reorganized in orientation
to this new authority.
Eventually, in modernity, the self
became the sovereign individual with
free will.
Our social, political, and legal
structures now worship it. Human rights,
private property, personal autonomy, you
name it. The sovereign individual has
been put on the throne. There are
different ways of coupling minds and
society, thought and communication
through the common medium of language.
Minds think about what is communicated.
Society communicates about what is
thought.
Thinking and communicating are organic
autopoietic processes like life,
functioning systemically
without agents that can be empirically
pinned down.
Try to find your soul or your true self.
But, there needs to be an imagined
nexus, an authoritative agent who
thinks, speaks, and provides
orientation. This orientation point is,
as Deep Seek puts it, an incredibly
effective illusion.
In ancient times, intelligent agency,
via sense of the gods, was outsourced to
them.
But then, the sense of self prevailed,
and insourcing intelligence to the self
proved to be more effective.
All of this,
the outsourcing and insourcing of
intelligence, the generation of
knowledge of what to do how,
and the organization of society
has to do with religion.
In a number of quite recent books,
Sapiens: A Brief History of Humankind,
Homo Deus: A Brief History of Tomorrow,
and Nexus: A Brief History of
Information Networks, Yuval Noah Harari
has covered these topics and talked
about the crucial role of religion.
His website shows an aphorism
presumably meant to summarize his
approach.
"History began when humans invented gods
and will end when humans become gods."
I like the first part of this aphorism,
but not so much second.
Google AI says that for Harari, religion
is a crucial imagined order
or social construct rather than a divine
truth
designed to unite large numbers of
people through shared myths.
For Harari, the invention of religion,
shared myths, and an imagined order of
the world was a big evolutionary game
changer. It enabled humans to cooperate
much more effectively and on a larger
scale. It was also a key factor for
social and technological progress
because religions, myths, and orders
collected, stored, and transmitted
practical knowledge of all kinds.
The gods and the spirits were an
incredibly effective illusion for
memorizing and retelling knowledge.
Religions were an interactive
encyclopedia.
Everyone was thinking religiously, and
society communicated religiously.
In religion, we find the same conflation
of I and we as in the sentence by Deep
Seek quoted at the beginning of this
video.
When the gods or their spokespeople gave
their commands, they spoke presumably in
the first person mode and said, "I."
But in fact, what they said was always
what we had already figured out. It was
society speaking to itself.
Religious speech codes all knowledge by
outsourcing it, and in this way, it
communicates it and makes it
collectively available.
Here's an example,
Polynesian navigation.
Roughly between 3,000 and 1,000 BCE,
that is, in Jaynes' bicameral period,
probably starting from the island of
Taiwan,
humans crossed the Pacific Ocean and
populated islands all the way to
Polynesia.
They relied on navigation skills based
on the observation of stars, water
currents, clouds, and birds.
This knowledge was stored and
transmitted in religiously coded oral
traditions, songs, and stories.
Nature was perceived as animated,
conveying reliable intelligence and
informing people about where they were,
where they needed to go to, and when and
why.
Religion coded the available data at the
time.
The collectively generated, memorized,
and enacted knowledge about water,
clouds, stars, and birds needed for
crossing the ocean.
Given the rather low storage capacity of
stories and songs, it's probably fair to
speak of small data in this case.
The outsourcing of intelligence was a
highly effective way of coupling thought
and communication, but the disk space of
orally transmitted religious
communication is limited.
From a Jaynes-like perspective, we can
assume a gradual transition from the
outsourcing of intelligence to an
animated nature, to eye idols, or a
Socratic daimonion,
to an insourcing, when the spirits and
gods remain silent, and people needed to
think on their own.
This happened along with a shift from
oral to written religion.
In the 1st millennium BCE, many
religions became writing-based.
Eventually, there were canons of holy
texts,
books collected and transmitted
knowledge, and made it authoritative.
The number of texts grew fast. New ones
were written all the time, while the old
ones were still there.
It was obvious that writing was done by
humans, and so the notion of individual
authorship began to take hold.
Here's one example from my research
field. The Daodejing, the first
foundational text of the Daoist
tradition,
probably stems from centuries of oral
traditions, going back at least to the
middle of the 1st millennium BCE.
The earliest known written versions from
around the 3rd century BC do not
indicate an author.
They are written down collections of
oral sayings. Then, in the 2nd century
BCE, the text is eventually ascribed to
a man named Laozi, and legends about how
he supposedly wrote it down begin to
circulate.
At this time, deep into the 1st
millennium BCE, there are already lots
of non-religious texts as well. Texts,
including religious ones, are now often
regarded as written by identifiable
authors.
People read texts in their own voice, or
they can't read, they hear someone else
read them out in a human and not in a
divine voice.
Along with the silence of the gods, the
rise of writing, and the partial
secularization,
intelligence is insourced to thinking
selves as authors and readers.
A long history of the disenchantment of
communication takes place.
Religion doesn't disappear,
but it loses its monopoly of collecting,
transmitting, and authorizing all
relevant knowledge.
With author-reader-based writing,
the number of data grows immensely.
We can call this medium data.
The age of medium data spans from early
written texts like the Daodejing and the
establishment of ancient libraries to
modern encyclopedia and education
projects that make all knowledge public,
first in the Enlightenment, and recently
in Wikipedia. The reorientation of
intelligence to an inner self, and the
replacement of the gods with the
individual author, was a very effective
move for getting from small data to
medium data.
What remained the same in small and big
data was that with these data, society
was speaking to itself. All the data,
all the communication, is produced in
society.
Only communication can communicate. Not
gods, and not even selves can
communicate. Let's not confuse the
psychological sense of gods, or the
psychological sense of self, with actual
gods or selves. Now, finally, to AI.
To be frank, how exactly AI works and
calculates is a mystery for me. I very
little technological understanding of
it. But this is not what this video is
about.
As mentioned, this is a philosophical
video about the existential orientation
to AI, compared with other existential
orientations to gods and selves.
To avoid confusion, it's prudent to
start with a terminological distinction
between different aspects of AI. First,
the hardware and the software, the
platforms. Let's call all of this AI
technology, or AI tech.
Second, what AI tech is actually doing,
all the computing and data processing at
work. Let's call this AI operations, or
AI ops.
And third, the output that is produced
by AI ops when they respond to prompts
like code they develop, an image they
design, or texts written by LLMs. Let's
call all of this AI communication, or AI
talk.
I mentioned Wikipedia as a potential
endpoint of the age of medium data.
But Wikipedia is internet-based.
Therefore, it's somehow already part of
big data, or isn't it?
Well, Wikipedia still functions on the
basis of personally authored texts,
individual people. It's possible to
trace who the contributors are,
write entries based on sources, which
again, in many cases, are attributed to
individual authors.
But LLMs, like most AI tech, work
differently. There's no author at work.
And the data that I use are not traced
back to authors.
LLMs, and AI tech in general, operate by
statistically and algorithmically
processing big data, regardless of
authorship. An immense amount of data is
accessible to AI tech. AI ops,
processing these data, produce AI talk.
You can give AI a task, and it responds
in natural language. We know this.
The magnitude of the data makes authors
obsolete. In light of the vast amount of
communication, who said what is of
little interest. What literally counts
for AI talk is which word is, both
hindsight and foresight, most likely to
follow another.
In big data, communication is liberated
from the selves that we are conditioned
to attribute communication to.
Most academic texts are now written with
the use of AI tech in various degrees.
Almost all my students use it in one way
or another.
I can more or less guess if an
assignment by a student, or text by a
colleague, is AI-generated.
I admit I don't like it. But why?
It's usually the bad students who turn
to AI to cheat.
But students have always cheated, and it
didn't make me feel frustrated in the
way the use of AI does. I kind of
respected a good cheater.
AI-generated student work is usually
correct, but it sounds so sterile, so
predictable, so simulated.
AI talk is right to the extent of being
wrong.
It kind of offends the expectation of
however flawed authorship.
It somehow said. There's a feeling of
loss, a loss of the familiar agent
behind the text, a loss of style,
a loss of personality, or more
precisely, a loss of a sense of self.
That somehow feels like an insult and a
threat.
And this is not only the case when
reading AI talk by others. If I use AI
and write with it, this too insults and
threatens my own sense of self.
The frustrated discomfort, the annoyed
sadness about a certain loss of selfhood
when reading or writing AI talk,
may be like the despair felt by that old
Assyrian statesman when he lamented
about the gods turning silent.
My god has forsaken and disappeared.
My goddess has failed me and keeps at a
distance.
The good angel who walked beside me has
departed.
When reading or writing AI talk, I have
a similar feeling. My good old sense of
self seems to have forsaken and seems to
retreat.
It fails me, keeps at a distance. The
good angel who walked beside me is
departing.
Let's go back again to Deep Seek's slip
of the tongue quoted at the beginning.
It said "I" and then switched to "we" as
the subject of the sentence.
It doesn't have a real "I". It's no one
in particular. It is "we", an instantly
calculated probability of speech, of a
transindividual "we",
relying on an immense collection of
communication data.
Precisely by abstracting from who said
what and only counting what has been
said and LLM has the artificial voice of
a collective us. But, based on the
concrete prompt or series of prompts, it
is fed by a person talking to it. It
generates a specifically tailored and
simulated I through which the big we
speaks.
Chat GPT and Deep Seek impersonate eyes
when we speak to them.
LLMs simultaneously impersonate millions
of eyes when they speak to millions of
people in any given time.
This reminds me of the multitude of
alabaster eye idols that impersonated
gods and could simultaneously speak to
thousands of prehistoric people 5,000
years ago.
The alabaster eye idols conveyed a sense
of gods.
The LLMs convey a sense of AI.
When speaking to AI, we develop a sense
of AI speaking back to us.
What is the power of this sense of AI?
The communicative power of AI tech lies
in big data. It's processing capacity is
so much bigger and faster than what can
be processed by minds and traditional
writing.
It radically breaks with the medium data
convention to tie those data to specific
authors.
By breaking the bond between what is
said and the self who said it, AI moves
beyond medium data. It's precisely the
outsourcing of the authority to
communicate that makes it such an
efficient other to talk to.
LLMs not only liberate communication
from intelligent selves, they also
dissolve the idea that in order to know
something, you must investigate what you
want to know.
An LLM knows nothing about the things
you asked it. It only computes what is
said about them.
In AI, there's no first order
observation.
When you ask an LLM about the meaning of
life, it doesn't look into the meaning
of life, but into the communication on
the meaning of life.
LLMs work exclusively with second-order
observations, the observations of
observations.
There's zero thought involved. AI ops
don't think and they don't observe
thought.
LLMs are second-order observation-based
communication machines completely devoid
of intelligence in the sense of the word
referring to minds. In this sense, AI is
not intelligent.
AI computes, it doesn't think.
Habitually though, when speaking to it,
we develop a sense of it as an agent, a
thing.
This thing is not a Cartesian res
cogitans, a thinking thing, but a res
loquens, a speaking thing. My Latin's a
bit rusty, please correct me if I'm
wrong.
Out of habit, we reify a someone we are
speaking with when we communicate. We
develop a sense of the speaker and then
make the speaker into a thing.
In the long-gone past, we made a thing
out of the sense of gods, the gods.
Then, we made a thing out of the sense
of self, the self.
Now it seems we're making a thing out of
the sense of AI we have when talking to
it and we call it artificial
intelligence.
But, as Deep Seek tells us, this AI as a
res loquens, a talking thing, does not
exist. It is just an incredibly
effective illusion. Gods do not exist,
but they are an incredibly effective
illusion for minds and society to
operate with small data.
Selves do not exist, but they are an
incredibly effective illusion for minds
and society to operate with medium data.
AI as a res loquens does not exist, but
it is an incredibly effective illusion
for minds and society to operate with
big data.
And yet, in big data times, the
situation is still the same as it was in
medium and small data times.
Only communication can communicate and
only thinking, that is mental systems or
minds, can think.
In AI talk, we, that is society, is
still talking to itself.
All the data in big data are social
data.
Machines statistically process language,
which is still nothing but
communication.
AI talk is still purely social.
As before, thought co-evolves with
communication.
Minds co-evolve with society.
Given the vast amount of AI talk, minds
now have a lot of stuff they can think
on.
And society will certainly be irritated
by these thoughts, as we can already
see.
What has changed is that communication
can now be digitally stored, processed,
and produced.
It is a big change for sure.
And this big change may very well result
in an existential reorientation.
In times of big data, we might need to
once more outsource the imagined
authority of intelligence.
And this reorientation
may be experienced as an existential
crisis.
Just as it was painful to say goodbye to
the gods and insulting to see them lose
their dignity,
it's painful to say goodbye to the self
and insulting to see it lose its
dignity. But, it seems that the self is
vacating the throne.
And that AI is going to be its
successor, even though none of them
actually exist.
I mentioned that this video is inspired
by a conversation with Iyad Rahwan.
This is a painting by him, oil on linen,
100 cm * 100 cm.
It's titled The Servers.
The title is a pun, obviously. The
computer servers at the center are
served by the human worshipers circling
them like the Kaaba in Mecca.
Humans become servers again. They
outsource intelligence like in religion.
Who's to judge if that's good or bad?
From a Daoist perspective, I suggest to
start with being stoic about it rather
than outraged, fearful, or depressed. We
can be gelassen or chill because we can
understand that AI, reified artificial
intelligence, does not exist.
What are the consequences of this
existential reorientation to AI?
As to technological or sociopolitical
changes, I don't know. I'm not a
prophet.
But, I venture some critiques of
currently popular speculations.
First, there has been a lot of mostly
dystopian prophecy about the coming of
the singularity, the big rupture, when
AI will become self-conscious and
supersede humans in intelligence and
take control of the world and whatnot.
The idea is similar to the vision of a
cyborg future when humans and machines
will be fused
like in so many science fiction
theoretical perspective, these scenarios
rely on the wrong assumption that AI is
actually intelligent. The assumption is
that AI ops function like brains or
minds. And often, minds and brains,
mental and biological systems, are not
even distinguished in these scenarios
and are identified with one another as
if they were the same.
According to systems theory, systems
evolve and emerge. Things don't get
less, but more complex over time.
Systems become more rather than less
differentiated.
Once they emerge, they tend not to fall
back into one another.
Broadly speaking, for instance, it seems
that mental systems evolved out of
biological systems and human society
emerged out of the duality of biological
and mental systems and made it a
systemic triad.
The singularity hypothesis suggests
something like a reversal. Bodies,
minds, and society all merge along with
machines back into one entity. They
become more simple and I don't think
that's likely.
If AI ops should become autopoietic, and
that's perhaps a possibility, a fourth
kind of self-reproducing
systemic realm of machines could emerge.
Luhmann too suggested this possibility.
I cannot predict what such an
autopoietic system would be like.
As mentioned, I hardly understand how AI
ops work, but it seems clear that they
work different from both minds and
brains. I mean, there are no biochemical
processes in the computers, unlike in
brains. And as the LLMs admit, they
don't think or feel. But they compute,
and perhaps there may be some sort of
autopoietic computing system in the
future.
So be it. I wish I'd be there to see
what happens then.
Philosophically, the singularity
scenario is rooted in the traditional
mind-body dualism. In classic dualism,
as in Plato and Descartes, mind and body
are in a struggle for mutual control.
Weak souls feel imprisoned in the body.
Our minds are in danger of being
controlled by bodily functions. Strong
souls look forward to be eventually set
free from the body altogether, or able
to keep the powers of the body in check.
So go the old stories.
There was a latent fear that the mind
may lose control, and a latent moral
demand that it ought to be in control.
The dystopian singularity scenarios
transform the fear of the mind being
controlled by the body into a new fear
of the mind being controlled by machines
that are more intelligent than them.
From a systems theory perspective, this
thought pattern is flawed. It's not just
that machines don't think, and that AI
as an intelligent agent doesn't exist.
It's also that systems do not and cannot
directly control one another. They
co-evolve in one another's environment.
They're feedback mechanisms, and through
these, each system evolves in its own
unpredictable way.
If a fourth system emerges, it probably
won't stop the other systems from
further co-evolving. The emergence of
consciousness also did not end or absorb
the evolution of biological life. And
neither did the emergence of society end
or absorb the evolution of
consciousness.
The traditional struggle for control
narrative also strongly influences
current AI ethics. Very fast, AI ethics
has become a formidable academic
sub-industry,
particularly in philosophy. There's
funding, there are publication
opportunities, there are job openings.
But theoretically, AI ethics tends to
approach the new technologies with the
old conceptual frameworks. AI ethicists
work on such things as self-driving cars
without racial or sexual orientation
prejudices.
And those that fund them, like the EU or
big tech corporations, are happy as long
as the ethicists don't challenge their
neoliberal techno-feudal regimes.
AI ethicists tend to see AI like
philosophers saw the body in the old
days, as a threat to human control and
autonomy. They want to make sure that
sovereign individuals continue to reign
supreme.
As if they ever did. As if minds had
ever been in control or autonomous.
Moralistic approaches to AI tend to
regard philosophy as an outside
corrective of AI. But in fact,
philosophical communication, like all
communication, is already intertwined
with AI talk. Academics, like everyone
else, are already in the loop. What they
say about AI is AI talk informed, and in
turn, it informs AI talk.
Academics, too, are part of the we of
big data. There's no communication
outside society. Philosophy happens
within it and is contingent upon it.
To sum up, the rise of AI signals an
existential reorientation,
a weakening of the sense of self, and a
strengthening of a sense of AI.
The supposed seat of intelligence is
outsourced again for very good reasons,
an incredible efficiency.
The habitual conditioning Deep Seek
mentions will be reconditioned. We can
no longer take it for granted that when
we communicate with someone, that this
someone is a thinking self. We will no
longer exclusively equate fluent
language use with an inner conscious
life, as Deep Seek said.
But with machines, we counterfactually
call intelligent.
But we can know that these machines are
not intelligent. They tell us so. And
that may be the decisive difference. The
gods were an effective illusion we
assumed did exist.
The self has been an effective illusion
we still assume exists.
Perhaps AI can be an effective illusion
of which we know that it does not exist.
This, in turn, has a lot to do with
prophylicity and genuine pretending.
But this is a topic for another video.
Get down, get down, get down, get down.